
Imam Nawawi's Introduction

In the Name of Allah, the Entirely Merciful, the Especially Merciful.

All praise (and thanks) is for Allah, the Rabb (ie: Lord) of the ‘Aalameen (ie: creation), the One who sustains the Heavens and the Earths, the One who manages all of the creation, the One who sent Messengers, Allah's Peace and Blessings be upon them, to accountable beings (ie: humans), to guide them and explain to them the Sharia (ie: laws) of the religion, with decisive evidences and clear proofs. I praise Him for all of His Blessings, and I ask Him for more of His Favors and Generosity. And I testify that there is no God (truly worthy of worship) except Allah alone, the One, the Supreme, the Generous, the Forgiving. And I testify that our master Muhammad is His slave and Messenger, and His beloved and Khalil (ie: close friend), the best of the creation, the one honored with the noble Quran, the lasting miracle throughout all the years, and (sent) with his Sunnah that lights (the way) for those who seek guidance, the one who is unique with (his) Jawami'ul Kalim (ie: concise speech) and easy religion. Allah's Peace and Blessings be upon him and all of the Prophets and Messengers, and each of their families and upon all of the righteous.

As for what follows: Indeed, we have narrated from Ali bin Abi Talib, Abdullah bin Mas’ood, Muaz bin Jabal, Abu Darda, Ibn Umar, Ibn Abbas, Anas bin Malik, Abu Huraira, Abu Saeed al-Khudri, may Allah be Pleased with them, through many chains with various narrations, that Allah’s Messenger, Peace and Blessings be upon him, said: “Whoever preserves 40 Hadith for my Ummah (ie: nation) from the affairs of its religion, Allah will raise him on the Day of Judgement among the ranks of the scholars and Faqihs (ie: learned men).” And in another narration: “Allah will raise him as a scholar and Faqih (ie: learned man).” And in the narration of Abu Darda: “And I (Muhammad) will be an intecessor and witness for him on the Day of Judgement.” And in the narration of Ibn Mas’ood: “It will be said to him: Enter from any of the doors of Paradise you wish.” And in the narration of Ibn Umar: “He will be recorded among the ranks of the scholars and will be gathered (on the Day of Judgement) among the Shuhada (ie: martyrs).”

And the Huffaz (ie: Hadith scholars) have agreed that it is a weak Hadith, even if its chains are many. And the scholars, Allah be pleased with them, have indeed authored inummerable works in this subject (of 40 Hadith). And the first I know of who authored in it was Abdullah bin al-Mubaarak, then Muhammad bin Aslam at-Toosi the Rabbani (Ie: firmly grounded) scholar, then Hasan bin Sufyan an-Nasai, and Abu Bakr al-Aajurri, and Abu Bakr Muhammad bin Ibrahim al-Asfahani, and Daraqutni, and Hakim, and Abu Nuaim, and Abu Abdurrahman as-Sulami, and Abu Saeed al-Maaleeni, and Abu Usman as-Saabooni, and Abdullah bin Muhammad al-Ansari, and Abu Bakr al-Baihaqi, and countless others from the earlier and later times.

And indeed, I have made Istikhara (ie: sought guidance) from Allah, the Highest, in collecting 40 Hadith, emulating these eminent Imams and Huffaz (ie: preservers) of Islam. And indeed, the scholars have agreed upon the permissibility of acting upon weak Hadith in Fadlail al-A'maal (ie: encouraging good deeds). Even so, my basis (for this collection) is not upon this (weak) Hadith, but rather upon his saying, Peace and Blessings be upon him, in Sahih (authentic) Hadith: “The one present among you should convey (what I say) to the one absent.” And his saying, Peace and Blessings be upon him: “May Allah brighten the (face of a) man who hears what I say and understands it, then conveys it just as he had heard it.” [Note: Sheikh Abdul Kareem bin Abdulla al-Khudlair said there was Tasaahul (unwarranted leniency) in Imam Nawawi's statement: "Indeed, the scholars have agreed upon the permissibility of acting upon weak Hadith in Fadlail al-A'maal", because Imam Nawawi stated there was agreement when there was Khilaf (differing). Sheikh al-Khudlair mentioned in his book: 'Weak Hadith and the ruling of using it as evidence' (page 259 onwards): The scholars differed regarding accepting weak Hadith. Some were of the view that weak Hadith cannot be acted upon at all, neither in Ahkam (legislative rulings) or Fadlail al-A'maal. And Sahih Hadith suffices a Muslim from needing Dlaeef Hadith. From the scholars of this view include: Muslim bin Hajjaj, Abu Zur'ah ar-Raazi, Abu Hatim ar-Raazi, Ibn Hibban, Abu Muhammad Ibn Hazm, Ibn Taimiyya, Muhammad bin Ali ash-Shaukani, Ahmad Muhammad Shakir, Muhammad Nasir ad-Deen al-Albani, as well as others. As for the other view, which is what the Jumhur (majority) of the scholars are upon, is that Dlaeef Hadith cannot be used as evidence in Ahkam (legislative rulings, Halal and Haram). But it can be used as evidence in Fadlail al-A'umaal. From the conditions for this is: The Hadith can't be very weak, it has to have a basis (in the established Sharia), it is not to be believed that the Hadith is authentic and  it is not to be affirmed to the Prophet ﷺ. From the scholars of this view include: Sufyan as-Sauri, Abdulla bin Mubarak, Abdurrahman bin Mahdi, Sufyan bin 'Uyaina, Ahmad bin Hanbal, Abu Umar bin Abdil Barr, Muwaffiq ad-Deen Ibn Qudama, Abu Zakariyya an-Nawawi, Ismail bin Kathir, Jaluddin as-Suyuti, as well as others.]

Then from the scholars were those who collected 40 (Hadith) on Usool ad-Deen (ie: fundamentals of religion), and some of them on Furoo' (ie: secondary branches of religion), and some of them on Jihad (ie: warfare), and some of them on Zuhd (ie: asceticism), and some of them on manners, and some of them on Khutbas (ie: sermons), and all of those are righteous purposes, May Allah be Pleased with those who intended them. And indeed, I see that a collection of 40 (Hadith) is more important than all of these, and that is 40 Hadith which encompasses all of that (mentioned before). And each Hadith from it is a great foundation from the foundations of religion, and indeed the scholars have described that Islam revolves around it, or it is half of Islam, or a third, and so on.

Afterwards, I oblige myself in (collecting) these 40 (Hadith) that they are to be Sahih (authentic), and most of them are in the two Sahihs, Bukhari and Muslim. And I mention them without their Sanads (ie: chains of narration), in order to make their memorization easy and their benefit widespread, if Allah the Highest Wills. Then I will follow them with a section on explaining their obscure phrases. [Note: This section is in the Sharh (ie: commentary) by Nawawi of his 40 Hadith, not his Hadith collection by itself.]

And it should be that everyone who desires the Hereafter should know these Hadith, because of what they encompass of important matters, and what they comprise in bringing to attention all obedience (to Allah). And that is clear to whoever thinks deeply about it. And upon Allah do I rely, and to Him is my trust and dependence, and for Him is all praise and blessings, and by Him is my success and protection from mistakes.