Translators Preface

مُقَدِّمَةُ الْمُتَرْجِمِ

بِسْمِ اللَّهِ الرَّحْمٰنِ الرَّحِيْمِ

الْحَمْدُ لِلَّهِ رَبِّ الْعَالَمِينَ. وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلَى رَسُولِ اللَّهِ، وَعَلَى آلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ أَجْمَعِينَ. اللَّهُمَّ لَا سَهْلَ إلاَّ مَا جَعَلْتَهُ سَهْلاً، وأنْتَ تَجْعَلُ الْحَزْنَ إذَا شِئْتَ سَهْلاً. ]أَخْرَجَهُ الَبَيْهَقِي فِي الدَّعَوَاتُ الْكَبِيرُ 266 وَابْنٌ حِبَّانِ فِي صَحِيحِهِ 0974 [سُبْحَانَكَ لَا عِلْمَ لَنَا إِلَّا مَا عَلَّمْتَنَا، إِنَّكَ أَنْتَ الْعَلِيمُ الْحَكِيم] .الْبَقَرَة ٣٢:٢ [

In the Name of Allah, the Entirely Merciful, the Especially Merciful.

All praise (and thanks) is for Allah, the Rabb (ie: Lord) of the ‘Aalameen (ie: creation). And Peace and Blessings be upon the Allah’s Messenger, and upon all of his family and companions. O Allah, there is no ease except for what You make easy, and You make the difficult, if you Will, easy. Exalted are you (from having any imperfections), we have no knowledge except what you have taught us, indeed you are the Knowing, the Wise.

Imam Nawawi was a great scholar of the Shafi'i Mazhab and a famous Imam. His name is Yahya bin Sharaf bin Murri bin Hasan bin Hussain bin Muhammad bin Jumu'ah bin Hizam. His Kunya is Abu Zakariyya. He was born on Muharram 631 H. (October 1233 AD.) in the city of Nawa, a place near Damascus, Syria. His title ‘an-Nawawi’ refers to his hometown.

Nawawi was blessed with sharp intelligence and the love of learning. Even at the age of 10, Nawawi was not interested in playing like the rest of the children. They would try to force him to play, and he would cry and flee from them, devoting his time to reciting the Quran. Nawawi memorized the Quran before reaching puberty. When he was 18, his father took him to Damascus to study there, which was the center of scholars and learning at that time. He would stay in a very small room filled with many books. He spent all his time seeking knowledge such that he would not even sleep except when it overtook him. He would fall asleep on his books, then awaken and continue studying. He never married. He was so busy attaining knowledge that that he would attend 12 lectures a day with his teachers on various Islamic sciences, not to mention his reviewing and memorizing of what he learned. Nawawi lived a simple and austere life. Eating only what he knew to be Halal and avoiding everything doubtful. He would even teach without accepting a salary. He was given the title ‘Muhyiddeen’ (ie: reviver of the religion), although he hated being called as such out of modesty.

During his 45 years of life, he authored many books covering various Islamic sciences, such as: 40 Hadith, Riyad as Saaliheen, al-Minhaj (Sharh of Sahih Muslim), at-Taqreeb wa-Taiseer on Hadith. Rawdlathu-Taalibeen, Minhaj at-Taalibeen, al-Majmu Sharh al-Muhazzab, on Shafi'i Fiqh, at-Tahrir fi Alfaz at-Tanbeeh on Arabic language, and many more. He died on Rajab 676 H. (December 1277 AD.) at his hometown Nawa. Although he passed away almost a thousand years ago, his knowledge continues to benefit us to this very day, via the enormous contribution he has left behind to the Muslim Ummah. May Allah forgive him and be Pleased with him. Ameen.

Nawawi's 40 Hadith is a comprehensive collection of Prophetic Hadith that cover the basic foundations of Islam in short, easy to read manner. Although brief, this work includes a range of topics such as: Islam, Iman (ie: faith), good deeds, Halal and Haram, brotherhood, charity, obedience, asceticism, manners, commanding good and forbidding evil, trusting in Allah, rememberance of Allah, and other important matters of religion. This famous compilation is continued to be taught and learned by Muslims, young and old, throughout history. And many renowned scholars have produced various commentaries and explanations based upon this book. It is recommended that students of knowledge begin memorizing Hadith by starting with these 40, before moving onto larger Hadith collections. Perhaps the reason for the wide spread acceptance of Nawawi's book and most Muslims being familiar with it is his sincerity, and Allah knows best. Imam Nawawi has discussed his own book and the reasons for writing it in his introduction that follows. Although the exact number of Hadith that Imam Nawawi included was 42  [Arabs would round off numbers], I have also mentioned after them the additional 8 Hadith that Ibn Rajab, the great Hanbali scholar, included in his commentary of Nawawi's 40 Hadith, which is the best known explanation on this book to date, titled ‘Jamiul Uloom wal-Hikam’. I have explained some phrases within brackets, and given titles at the beginning of each Hadith, to make things easier for the reader.

The Prophet ﷺ said: “Whoever does not thank (and be grateful to) the people, does not thank (and is not grateful to) Allah.” [Tirmidhi 1954, Abu Dawud 4811] All praise and thanks be to Allah for granting the Thaufeeq (ie: success) to complete this book. I would also like to thank everyone who helped in producing this work, translating difficult Arabic phrases, correcting mistakes in the text, reviewing and checking everything, etc. May Allah give them constant abundant reward for their efforts. Any good this brings is from Allah, and any shortcomings are from ourselves and shaithan. May Peace and Blessings be upon our Prophet Muhammad.

اللَّهُمَّ رَبَّ جَبْرَائِيلَ وَمِيكَائِيلَ وَإِسْرَافِيلَ، فَاطِرَ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضِ، عَالِمَ الْغَيْبِ وَالشَّهَادَةِ، أَنْتَ تَحْكُمُ بَيْنَ عِبَادِكَ فِيمَا كَانُوا فِيهِ يَخْتَلِفُونَ، اهْدِنِي لِمَا اخْتُلِفَ فِيهِ مِنَ الْحَقِّ بِإِذْنِكَ، إِنَّكَ تَهْدِي مَنْ تَشَاءُ إِلَى صِرَاطٍ مُسْتَقِيمٍ. ]رَوَاهُ مُسْلِمٌ 0770 [

“O Allah, Rabb of Jibril, Mikail and Israfil, Originator of the Heavens and Earth, Knower of the Unseen and Seen, You Judge between Your Slaves in what they used to differ in, guide me to (make me steadfast upon) the truth by Your Permission in what they differed in, indeed, You Guide whom You Will to Sirat al-Mustaqim (ie: the Straight Path).”
